Hey, Brandon here. This is the bonus
companion video to my worldbuing Q&A
lecture. So, if you have been following
along for each of the topics for my
lecture series, which is now finished,
I'm recording a bonus Q&A. And these are
your questions about world building
taken from the Q&A episode that happened
in my class. Uh, number one, in your
lectures, you talk about having
worldbuilding be a hollow iceberg. What
are some signs or signals to us as
writers that we've gone off the deep end
with world building and our iceberg has
become too dense? Similarly, how can we
self assess our own work to see if the
iceberg needs to be deeper and the world
building needs to be more comprehensive?
Seems like a very fine line to tread and
I'd love to hear your thoughts. Well,
um, thank you. Uh, thank you for the
question. This is a fine line to tread.
So, let's start with the first one. How
can you tell if your world building if
you're putting too much world building
into the book? Uh, I would suggest a
two-phase litmus test. The first one is,
are you spending so much time worldbuing
that you aren't actually getting to your
writing? Uh, this is the first and most
important of the litmus tests. Uh, when
we talk about people spending too much
time worldbuing, really we're talking
about they spend so much time upfront
that they never actually get to the
story. Uh, now this can be totally fine
if that is your goal, right? We're
taking the the focus that you want to be
a professional writer. If what you want
to do is spend 20 years worldbuilding
the perfect world and then write some
stories in it, I'm not going to stop
you. There's nothing wrong with that. Uh
but if your goal is to make a living as
a science fiction fantasy novelist, you
need to be releasing uh stories
regularly. And so from that end, if you
are spending so much time worldbuing
that you aren't able to hit your
personal writing deadlines, then that's
when it starts to be a problem. Uh, for
instance, I would recommend that most
authors be shooting for trying to
complete one book a year um in a of a
normal length sort of book. One book
every two year is acceptable. If you're
going over about one book every two
years, then and you're spending a ton of
time world building, I would recommend
shifting some of that to writing. One of
the things that's going to be a problem
here is a lot of you newer writers,
you're not going to know where you
actually need to spend your world
building time until you get better
writing instincts. The more you write,
the more your world building time ahead
of time on your book will become more
effective. So, build those writing
instincts. See what you need. Um, there
is no wrong way to write a book. And
some books have huge, dense, full of
worldbuing openers that are of the style
the author wants them to be. That's not
wrong. A steep learning curve does, you
know, cut out some of your audience, but
it gains you other people that really
enjoy that. Uh Steven Ericson is a great
example of this. But even um there are
lots of famous books that are very
worldbuilding heavy straight up front.
Snow Crash does a ton of very bizarre,
very interesting worldbuilding things
straight in your first chapter. You're
thrown straight in and you have to deal
with this this wacky, fascinating,
interesting world. That's not wrong. In
fact, Snow Crash is one of the great um
pieces of science fiction literature.
And so at this point you your second
litmus test is for the goals that you
have. Are you turning off your reader
because you're not giving them stakes,
character, and story and instead are you
letting yourself lapse into wanting to
put the world building in because you
spent the time on it. That's the your
second big thing that uh that people
have a problem with with world building
too much. They spend so much time on the
history that when it doesn't match the
storytelling, you still just want to put
in paragraphs and paragraphs of
explanations. Again, if this is the
story you're telling, it doesn't have to
be wrong. Uh but oftent times that will
turn readers off a little bit. Uh
they'll say, "Why does this connect?
What's the point?" Um the other side, if
you're will you're looking for your
world building to be more comprehensive.
Well, uh, generally your biggest problem
here is going to be reader confusion.
Uh, and I rely on early readers for
this. You're reading, they're reading
the book and they're like, I can't pay
attention to the characters because I
don't know what questions to be asking
about the magic system. I don't know if
I'm asking the right questions. I'm just
confused. And usually that's not what
you want. There are certain types of
stories again where you want people
confused a little at the beginning, but
you pair those with really dynamic
storytelling to pull them through the
confusion as you're relying on this the
realizations that come later to really
build a um a connection between them and
the and the story. If you were blind
reading a book and had to tell a prayer
writer from an amateur solely based on
worldbuilding, what were the symptoms
you'd be look what would be the symptoms
you're looking for? Um, excellent
question. As I said in the class,
oftentimes you can tell a pro from an
amateur uh very quickly the same way
that you could tell a pro piano player
from a an amateur piano player. Well,
with this there's a few little things
I'd be looking for. Um, the first would
be, uh, how many names are you throwing
at the reader? Straight up. You usually
want to keep proper names down a little
in your openings. You want to focus on
the character and their names. Uh, you
don't want to hit us too much. Once in a
while, it can be good for setting a tone
uh, and whatnot. Uh, but people's eyes
will start to glaze over and this can be
one of your dangerous areas,
particularly in a fantasy book. Throwing
a ton of names and jargon and terms,
unless you're shooting for that really
steep learning curve on purpose, uh, is
one of those things that'll make you
stand out. Uh, the other sorts of
things, well, uh, you will look amateur
if you look like you're trying to show
off your world building rather than
letting it be there to enhance the
story. If uh you are so excited by your
world building that we have paragraphs
and paragraphs of info dumps rather than
a character doing something, then you
have a problem. And what the pros are
going to do, even if they have a really
exciting magic system, uh there's a book
called Spellright, which is an an
excellent example of this, which is
people creating spells. It's a it's a
it's a an excellent book that I
recommend. And the opening scene is a
character basically trying to debug a
spell. The problem being he's dyslexic
and he's in class for writing spells and
they're actually physically written
spells. It's a really cool innovative
magic system, but there's a character
with a problem and his personal um
limitations then lead to the part making
the problem worse um through no fault of
his own which immediately builds us
sympathy and rooting interest. It shows
off the magic system as he is debugging
it essentially. a really good opening
for a magic systemheavy first chapter.
The reader who reads that will know very
quickly if this is a good book for them.
Um whereas you pair that with the
amateur and you'll end up with this
long- winded sort of in the dawn of time
there was a magic that was and there's
no characters to latch on to. um there's
this over wrought, overwritten opening
that uh feels kind of purple and it's
just like a big barrier to getting into
the story. That's one of the things
world building specifically that you
would look at. Now, of course, the main
things are going to be how well the
reader um how well the author can handle
voice and how well they can get across
this world building um through the way
the character sees the world. That's a
hybrid between character and world
building. Uh but it is, as I say in
class, the grand skill of writing
science fiction fantasy is the ability
to convey your world through the eyes of
a character. So, you don't even realize
as a reader that the world building is
happening. Instead, you feel like you're
getting character and plot. How do you
make your world's history relevant to
the storyline? How do you make the
history described in the books
surprisingly relevant? I'm always
impressed at how every bit of historical
context given in your books ends up
being crucial to the plot. War breaker
is a wonderful example of this. Uh well,
thank you. Um again, so how do you make
the history relevant? So your easiest
way to make things relevant um on that
first question is to make them
interesting to the characters in some
way. uh the reader if they can pick up
on the relevance uh early on because
it's important to a character, they'll
pay better attention. And particularly
if you're going to be using this history
for important things later on, you want
them to have paid some attention. And a
lot of times what you're doing here is
you're doing a bit of a you're
signposting that they should be paying
attention for a reason different than
the fact that there's a twist coming.
You make the character interested in it.
You make it their passion. you make the
character ignorant about it. And the um
the real point of the scene that the
reader thinks is this is the two
characters chatting about something and
there's a subtext of either like romance
or argument or things like this and
they're paying attention because they're
fascinated by that and then the clues
you have inserted about history become
extra relevant later on. Um your where
your character's focus is is where your
reader's focus should be. Um, usually
those things match up exactly and if
you're writing well they will. But um,
how do you make it uh, surprisingly
relevant? Well, this be uh, this comes
from understanding what you need to
foreshadow and uh, a lot of times it
comes from knowing what your ending is
before you're writing or revising. If
you are a discovery writer, it's okay.
uh you get to that ending and then you
do a good revision where you say, "Okay,
these are the key things that I need
that are crucial. How can I devise
scenes early on that convey this
information without looking
heavy-handed?" And it's that
heavy-handedness that you really need to
watch for as a new writer. Um having the
storyteller come on and the point of the
story, you know, oftentimes wits, the
point of wit story is to motivate in a
certain way. the reader's watching for
those motivation context clues. When
something becomes relevant later on um
with Hoy's story and you're like, "Oh, I
learned that history." That's really
fun. I thought I was just learning about
um you know, Hoy giving a pep talk. Um
you know, find ways to make everything
you're doing achieve more than one goal.
And with these history lessons, what you
don't want is a history lesson. You want
a fun and interesting dynamic scene
where things are happening.
um and people are excited. Another way
to make these interesting is to somehow
make them visual. This is why when uh
Whit is telling the the story of the
water sail, he is using some
lightweaving. He knows that an audience
needs something more to really bond to
than just a story. And it can be as
simple as throwing uh powders into the
air as I have him do. Uh a lot of books
will have, you know, visual context in
some way. Uh, it's the reason that Maui
has tattoos in Moana, so that when a
story happens, you have a visual
representation of that story. They don't
have to necessarily flashback. You've
got a cool means of telling the story.
Uh, look for these sorts of things to
keep people engaged and interesting when
they're on the screen. And then pay them
off. The more often you pay them off,
the more people will want to pay
attention later on. All right. I am
working on a story as told by the spirit
or god of the city in which it takes
place. and the viewpoints from
characters all different points in time.
Very cool. Very ambitious. Uh I approve
before they ultimately all converge in
the main timeline. Okay, great. Some
cloud atlas sort of stuff going on here.
Um do you have any suggestions for how
to pull off nonlinear storytelling? I'm
using third person limited storyteller
for the narration. All right. Um, so one
of the things to be aware of is that
readers will naturally bond to um
whatever they consider the main timeline
most. And it'll be extra work to get
them to care about the other timelines.
And that's just something you have to
overcome. Make sure that each of them
has a hook that makes them distinctive,
a narrative hook that is somehow
interesting. And if you can early on
start to tease that these things are
going to be relevant to each other,
every little little bit of relevance,
the reader early on will latch on to um
and be like, "Oh, that's important."
Even if it's something as simple as um
Dallinar mentioning his knife again, the
knife that was in a flashback, and be
like, "Man, I like that knife." Um,
right? Just to tie them together to to
give that little hit of, oh, these are
going to be relevant. Um, and start that
early. Start promising that convergence
long before it happens so that readers
subconsciously start to say, "Okay, this
is all relevant. This is all meaningful.
Um, this is all important." You're going
to have less of a problem with this
style of story than you will with
flashbacks. uh which might seem odd to
you because they're all different
characters, but readers early on are
going to see this premise and be like,
"Oh, I see what's happening. It's a cool
nonlinear thing." And once again, people
will self- select into liking this story
um as you open and kind of let it dawn
on them what it is. And that's going to
mean that the people that this story is
for are going to keep reading. And if
you can pay off for them, don't worry
about paying off every story for
everyone. pay off for the people that
are going to love the fact that you're
doing a nonlinear um narrative. And
that's how you do it. You start to give
these clues that things are going to um
come together. You're going to want to
while they're reading, they're really
going to want to see things in one
timeline have an influence on another
timeline. You're going to want to see
parallels. One of the stronger nonlinear
um narratives and even is uh is Doomsday
Book by Connie Willis in which one
character goes back in time and is
experiencing the bubanic plague while a
modern um pandemic is happening in the
future. and the ways that the science
fiction timeline deals with the pandemic
versus the helplessness of the people in
the past timeline um gives us all of
that thematic uh both contrast and um
parallelism that we want uh in really
interesting ways. And of course, most of
the book is about the past. And so the
flash the the future ones are very brief
and don't overstay their welcome. And uh
it works really really well for that
reason. It's a it's an excellent example
of doing this. So, uh, hopefully that
will help you. I do think you'll have
less trouble than you think, uh, because
people will quickly pick up on what type
of story this is. Um, and they will
bond, uh, to watching it all come
together. That's going to be their
progress. The process of world building,
how do you measure your progress on
world building? Is it by word count,
section? Do you write formally, or note
format? Do you set a deadline for your
world building and then just let that
pass? or would you carry on? So, usually
I work via a deadline for my world
building. I say, "Okay, I've got this
much time before I'm going to start
writing." The thing to remember is, even
though I'm a heavy outliner, I am
generally going back to my notes guide
uh a lot during the early parts of the
book and writing a chapter, filling it
out. Uh if you've been following the
progress of uh Ghost Bloods on my weekly
updates, you'll see that some weeks I
only get a couple percentage points and
other weeks I get the full four that I
want. That's because I say I'm diving
back into world building for this week.
I've written enough of a chunk that I
know what I'm going to need later on.
Let's go and make sure that's all uh in
place. Uh my world building is generally
uh a mix of paragraphs explaining and
bullet points just giving a list. Uh
early on it's paragraphs. later on it
turns into bullet points which might
seem reversed to you but that is the way
it happens is as I'm exploring the world
I'm kind of talking my way through it
and as it starts to click into place
then all I need is the bullet points
because this is only for me I've already
got the general feel I just need
reminders on some things and so this is
for a new book uh by the way uh what's
um my process like is it by word count
uh no the whole thing does tend all of
my notes on character setting plot
together tend to be about 10% word count
of what the final book will be.
100,000word book tends to have around
10,000 words of world building. Uh but
that's not a hardf fast rule and I don't
look to keep that rule. I've just
noticed that theme as I do it. Uh so I
don't look for a word count. I look for
a do I feel confident in this setting
and can I start writing and when I hit a
point where I need to build something
more and this is something really
important that uh those of you who have
worldbuilder disease you won't be able
to anticipate all the things that you're
going to need. So it often is better to
start writing and then hit okay I need
this let's spend a little bit more time
in my world building here. Just don't
let it interrupt your writing too much.
Uh and I do that quite a bit. I'm like,
"All right, what's the theme for this?
Let's jump back to my notes document,
write out a few paragraphs so I have it
later on." All right, I feel comfortable
on that. Back to the writing. How often
should you describe the spice, quote
unquote, just the poor practice in the
first place, or is there a way to use
the same principles without a physical
description of location? Um, so, uh,
again, there's no one way to do this,
but I'm glad you're asking this
question. Uh, it is a relevant question.
Uh, how often? Again, no rule here. What
you want to do is remember that kind of
pyramid of distraction. Uh, you want to
start a scene by pulling the reader into
that scene, either with characters
launching like straight into a problem
or something like that. Um, if you start
with dialogue, make sure you set the
scene at some point. Uh, every chapter
should set the scene, even if it's in
the same place. Have the character
notice something different or whatnot.
Uh, I have a lot of characters out in
the mists in Mistbornne. And each time
I'll set the scene, I'll do it from the
character's viewpoint. Today, they're
feeling like this, and the mists seem
playful. Today, the mists seem kind of
dark and ominous because the character's
mood is such there could be anything
hiding in there. uh to at one time the
mists are lighter and so um they might
describe it in one way at another time
they're deeper and thicker or there's
certain lights. Basically finding
different ways to describe the same
thing. Someone's in the same room all
the time. you know, use a few sort of
clues like there's a clock that's always
ticking in the corner and today that
beat seemed to be to the song that he
had been singing earlier or uh today
that clock ticking was really annoying
or whatever it is so that you're
reminding us of what the setting is. set
that scene, put the character in the
scene, and then you can go, you can go
through the rest of the chapter without
doing a lot of the scene setting, except
for occasional reminders of having the
character interact with it. Uh,
interacting with the scene to pull us
back into it is really handy. You'll see
people doing this a lot in film as well.
um after there's a long conversation,
they push out of their chair and they
like, you know, slam on the table or
they lean against the wall or something
like this that is doing the exact same
thing. It is pulling us out of the
abstract into the concrete, reminding us
that these aren't talking heads, that
these are characters in a setting. Um
and interacting with that setting is
really just very handy. Um how often do
you describe the spice in Dune? Um,
you're talking about how the spice kind
of sparkles in the air. Um, I would do
it any time that a character is pausing
and looking across the setting. I might
not describe the spice in detail every
time. I might just throw it in a line,
but I would include it in each of your
setting details. Just like in mistboard,
uh, every time someone's outside,
they're going to describe the mist. And
finding ways to just make this work uh,
and not feel too redundant is part of
your job as a writer. uh finding ways to
set I mean you're gonna have to write so
many scenes that take place in a room
with two people talking to each other.
Practicing how to make that scene
description interesting by seeing it
through the character's viewpoint and
mood for that day is one of the things
you need to learn as a writer. So I'm
glad you're asking this. Um and uh I
would recommend that you just uh you
just practice it that focus on that and
see what you can do. I wouldn't say the
lack of scenery change for a character
is poor practice. Um there are lots of
great stories that take place in a
single room. And so I mean Emperor Soul
is my award winner and 90% of that story
takes place in one room. I'm finding
ways to make that room evolve and change
in order to keep it fresh and whatnot,
but uh definitely not poor practice to
keep someone in the same place. Just
depends on the story you're telling. All
right, last question. Is there a way to
blend divine entities with mortals
without making them feel disconnected
from the primal primal instincts of the
worlds or overpowered compared to
mortals? Uh a mix of sylmerelion and
Narnia for example. Well uh it is
definitely a thing that I am doing. Um
whether it's effective or not is uh is
your mileage may vary. I do a lot of
this in wind and truth. Uh in fact um so
yes there are plenty of ways to do that.
Uh one thing to to keep in mind is uh
motivations can be uh can cross all
sorts of boundaries of um alien biology
and divine natures and things like that.
If somebody cares about something that's
relatable, well, it won't really matter
who they are or what their power are.
That care, that passion is going to pull
us through. If someone is prevented from
doing something they want to do, we know
what that feels like. Even if um some
sort of divine figure is doing it. Now,
uh there is a reason why the gods in the
cosmir feel more a little more like
Greek gods and a little less like
omnipotent um um divinities. And I'm I'm
kind of in between those two. More than
a Greek god, less than an omnipotent
divinity. uh and that is because I do
want to make them relatable and I do
need them to be viewpoints now and then
but I use them sparingly uh because I do
think it is difficult to get someone to
bond to someone who is doing that much.
You can or is capable of that much. You
can absolutely do this. Uh there are
stories that do this. It depends on the
conflict. It depends on what your
theming for uh that viewpoint is. Um,
and I guess my answer to you is yes,
it's very possible, but there are as
many ways to do this as there are
authors who might try it. So, you're
going to have to find your own uh method
of doing this and um ways to make
rooting interests and to make people
fascinated by these characters. And you
might just use pros to do that. Uh, a
very distinctive and interesting pros
might be the method. Or you might make
uh use the Superman problem. What makes
Superman interesting? the things he
can't do. What are the overpowered
individuals incapable of doing? That
might be where your story is. You could
go either direction on those. So, uh
there you are. Those are your worldbuing
questions. Uh thank you so much. We have
one more of these videos that we are
prepping which is going to be the um the
nature of publishing and uh the bonus
video on that. And then we will wrap up
uh this series for now. So, hey, thank
you so much for your questions and uh I
hope that that was helpful.